<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ania Aizman's teaching portfolio &gt; past courses &gt; Art and Anarchism &gt; student projects</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2020 16:41:10 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2020 16:41:10 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Anarcho-Punk and Gender Politics</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the emergence of radical political movements and anarchist art in the late 20th-
century came the rise of feminist punk culture within the broader anarcho-punk scene. Art forms
such as Riot Grrl zines, DIY culture, and all-female bands created an anarcho-punk culture that
coincided with third-wave feminist values of the time. Contrary to those who might argue that
feminist punk is dead or has lost momentum since its surge in the ‘90s, scholarly work has
shown that there is a strong existing presence of women in punk. By analyzing studies on gender
politics within anarchist cultures, I argue that women’s voices in the anarcho-punk scene have
existed and flourished in contemporary society with post-modern feminist tactics, despite efforts
to drown them out inside and outside of anarcho-punk culture. I will look at zines, song lyrics,
and public statements from different artists and bands including the popular feminist protest
group from Russia, Pussy Riot. These artists have put women’s issues at the forefront in their
anarcho-punk music and politics and therefore will enrich my study of women in punk. I will
also analyze the existing literature on gender politics within anarcho-punk in an attempt to
understand how women have used strategies of resistance to shape their identities in society and
within punk culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background-on-women-in-punk&quot;&gt;Background on Women in Punk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The role of women in punk began and flourished in the ‘70s-’90s with the rise of female
musicians in rock bands and independent punk literature. In the United States, the Equal
Opportunities Act and third-wave feminism created opportunities for women to participate in
once non-traditional spaces to voice their political beliefs and frustrations with the gendering of society. Bands and artists of the time such as Patti Smith, Bikini Kill, Poison Girl and more,
challenged these structural inequalities through anarchist principles. American philosopher
Noam Chomsky defines anarchism as “a tendency that is suspicious and skeptical of domination,
authority, and hierarchy. It seeks structures of hierarchy and domination in human life over the
whole range, extending from, say, patriarchal families to, say, imperial systems, and it asks
whether those systems are justified…” (as seen in Davis, 2019). Poison Girl uses this sentiment
in their music with lyrics stating “Take the toys from the boys, take their hands off the guns”
which challenges gender and masculine pride specifically (LeBlanc, 1999 p. 49). In the early
‘90s, Riot Grrrl emerged from the male-dominated punk cultures of the time as a new form of
anarcho-punk. The Riot Grrrl Manifesto in the Bikini Kill Zine states: “We are angry at a society
that tells us Girl = Dumb, Girl = Bad, Girl = Weak” (as seen in D'Angelica, 2009 pg. 2). Riot
Grrrl and other feminist punks were concerned with the struggles surrounding women in US
society including violence against women and the right to choose, although their approach
differed from the mainstream political route with capitalist media (D'Angelica, 2009 pg. 2).
Ultimately, this new subculture of anarcho-punk culture created a space for women to
deconstruct notions of gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although punk culture has changed since its heyday during the era of Patti Smith and
Riot Grrrl, ‘DIY’ or ‘do it yourself' anarcho-punk culture has continued into the 21st century and
evolved into a movement of many subcultures including anarcha-feminism with ethos generally
coinciding with post-structural feminism. The internet has become a popular tool for independent
artists and Zine creators to share new music and literary works. Large punk databases and
websites act as outlets for people to independently publish their creative works of anarchist-ethos
and feminist politics. Similar to anarcha-punk in the late-20th century, women have used creative expression to deconstruct social norms around identity politics through music, literature and
other forms of art while also applying more intersectional feminist ideals to their work. I will
later explore specific examples of these works in order to better understand the ways in which
punk culture has continued and evolved to construct various identities in the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-women-in-punk-toolkit&quot;&gt;The Women in Punk Toolkit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women in contemporary punk cultures have learned and developed different tools to help
them navigate spaces within and outside of masculine punk cultures. In a study of girls in punk
subcultures, Lauraine LeBlanc argues that punk is still alive and that youth, in particular, are
attracted to the anti-authority spirit and heavily contribute to the maintenance and development
of punk (LeBlanc, 1999 pg. 34). Through in-depth ethnographic research, she goes into further
detail about the ways in which these young women utilize tools of resistance against these
oppressive behaviors and concludes that “girls in male­dominated youth subcultures such as
punk continually confront ideologies of gender that remain largely invisible…gender is
problematic for punk girls in a way that it is not for punk guys because punk girls must
accommodate female gender within subcultural identities that are deliberately coded as made”
(LeBlanc, 1999 pg. 9). LeBlanc provides insight into the various ways in which women are
viewed within the punk culture and how they react to the gender dynamics to shape their own
identities. This is important in understanding the difficulties women often face in male-
dominated space. Although there are many women actively participating or eager to participate
in punk culture, there are regularly occurring oppressive cultural limitations imposed by men in
the form of overt and covert sexism and homophobia and must find creative ways to combat
gender inequality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Leblanc points to ways in which adolescent women in punk internalize and
conform to some of the gender norms of femininity and heterosexuality in order to feel as if they
belong in the subculture and are accepted by the men (LeBlanc, 1999 pg. 105). These obstacles
might help to explain why women are considered less visible in punk spaces. If women must
minimize resistant ideology and behavior in order to be allowed to participate within a group,
their presence will, in turn, be minimized within the anarcho-punk subculture. However, this is
just one strategy women deploy while establishing themselves within punk culture and can help
make sense of the complexities of gender politics within punk culture. Alternative strategies
include vocally and physically negotiating between norms of masculinity and femininity and
positioning themselves outside of mainstream cultures (LeBlanc, 1999 pg. 13). The concept of
“tools of resistance” introduced by Leblanc, can be used to analyze recent anarcha-punk works in
relation to their power struggles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;punk-zines&quot;&gt;Punk Zines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When members of the ‘90s band Bratmobile and Bikini Kill started the Riot Grrrl movement,
Molly Neuman, Allison Wolf, and others wrote an editorial statement as a tool to collectivize
individuals towards a movement of solidarity amongst women in punk who were experiencing
similar forms of sexist discrimination:“…there has been a proliferation of angry grrrrl zines in
recent months, mainly due to the queezy feeling we girls get in our stomachs when we
contemplate the general lack of girl power in society as a whole, and in the punk underground
specifically” (as seen in Allen, 2011). This Riot Grrrl spirit exists to this day in the form of print
and online Zine publications and can be seen in popular revolutionary corpuses such as
CrimethInc.com and smaller-scale blogs such as “The Permission Factory”. In 2013, this blog
was created to include a set of zines from queer people exploring gender and sexuality politics through a collective space that encouraged positive discourse and support for writers and readers.
Creator of “The Permission Factory,” Scott Treleaven, explained his fascination with zines and
motivation for the blog: “We’re a sextet of simultaneously emerging publications closely linked
by our paradoxically uniform mix of paganism, sexual libertinism, cult aesthetics, anti-
mainstream gay stance…that none of us have never met before, but were all compelled to enter a
similar discourse, still amazes me” (Allen, 2011 pg. 143). Although zine culture has changed
from the ’90s to present day—from their general topics of discussion to mode of
communication—they both enact similar strategies of solidarity amongst participants in order to
maintain and develop their anarcha-punk ethos. The collective efforts of ‘do it yourself’ culture
is used as a key tool for punk women to unite against oppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zines often arise out of frustration with specific events in contemporary society, such as
the #MeToo movement, and serve as an alternative source to the mainstream media to talk about
feminist issues. In a study of gender and post-structuralist, Lucy Nicolas argues that the anarcha-
punk uses post-structuralist strategies of autonomy, self-empowerment or self-creation within
zines and other punk outlets, which is then adapted to gender politics to transcend gender as a
tyrannical, authoritarian discursive site of undesirable order (Nicholas, 2007 pg. 18). This can be
seen in the Zine titled, “Fuck Abuse, Kill Power,” which looks at the compounding power
structures that have impacted the law regarding sexual violence. The anonymous author writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have to weave together the ways that we respond to specific instances of
sexual harassment and violence with a determination to confront and undermine
the social order that gives rise to them. In every case of male violence, we should
be clear that we are not dealing with an exception, but with a problem that is a
structural feature of our society. At the same time, we need to create models of
transformative justice that can replace the criminal justice system without
replicating any feature of it, and to foster new ways of relating in which
patriarchy, white supremacy, and other forms of authority do not determine the
possibilities of our lives. Every person of every gender stands to gain from this.
Let us join hands, teeth bared (9).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This example illustrates the ways in which women in modern punk cultures use zines as a
platform of autonomy, self-empowerment and self-creation. This anarcha-punk tool allows the
author to express their frustrations with the wave of sexual violence in the past year and the
issues with the criminal justice system as an ineffective means of solving the problem. The
author also emphasizes the significance of spreading this message through outlets detached from
capitalist media. This embodies the ‘do it yourself’ or ‘DIY’ ethic as the punk subcultures to
create art that is separated from hierarchies and capitalist markets. Post-structural feminism
works as a strategy to deconstruct gender norms within the anarcho-punk culture and mainstream
society within these forms of expression. The zine also includes an image of a king gripping his
sword while sitting in a burning throne with the caption “Patriarchy is not the bad behavior of a
few specific men, but the framework of relations that fosters it.” The use of irony and other
literary techniques within DIY culture shows how the constructed barriers of gender can be
broken down through art. The ethos of autonomy and self-creation of DIY are thereby contingent
on postmodern feminist and anarchist movements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;punk-music&quot;&gt;Punk Music&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Masculine-dominated punk subcultures can create toxic environments which exclude
women from participation, forcing them to perform resistant strategies to gain access. In a study
of women in punk music cultures in the UK, Naomi Griffin found that DIY punk music scene
and leftist subcultures have ignored and sometimes contradicted the social progression of certain
minority groups. Griffin argues the punk music scene acts as a natural space for the resistance to
oppressive beliefs and institutions, however, masculine bodily performances might diminish the
inclusive space that punk ethos aspires to create. For example, heavy metal music can encourage
pushing, head-banging, and aggressive dance moves that are understood as more comfortable for men to perform than women (Griffin 2012). Bodily performances such as this might discourage
women from attending punk music events out of fear of being injured or ostracized.
Additionally, song lyrics of the bands in this ethnography often discussed leftist and anarchist
political ideology on certain topics such as homophobia and racism, while simultaneously
objectifying women in their songs and album images. This explains why some women might feel
more uncomfortable in a punk music setting compared to men, which might help answer why
there are fewer well-known female anarcho-punk bands, or why female bands often emphasize
intersectional feminist politics in their lyrics. Because of this culture, it is necessary for women
in punk music to use employ different tools in order to shape their identities within an anarcho-
punk space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of a contemporary band using resistant strategies within anachro-punk music
to spread feminist ideals is the Russian, left-wing female group, Pussy Riot, who became widely
known after performing “Punk Prayer” in the Cathedral of Christ the Saviour in Moscow.
Political Science scholar Janet Johnson looks at Pussy Riot's “Punk Prayer” and other protest
performances as a reaction to the Kremlin's masculinity-based nation-rebuilding scheme, which
was a cover for homophobic ideology (Johnson 2014). Although Pussy riot is responding to a
different feminist context based on their country’s hierarchies and forms of oppression, their
anarchist ethos can be analyzed as a cross-cultural technique to position themselves outside of
mainstream culture. This can also be seen in their 2018 song “Bad Girls” which says: “Good
girls working at the banks; Bad girls blowing up the tanks; Good Girls pray to a man with a
beard; But God is a woman and she’s deaf and she’s queer; Good girls are waiting on the kings;
And the bad girls are laughing;‘Cause they know he’s a dick.” Pussy Riot challenges notions of
femininity by comparing traditional gender roles to an anarcha-feminist ideology. This strategy works to break down constructions of identity by ironically comparing “bad girls,” who
challenge authority to “good girls,” who remain subjected to gender norms. It also critiques the
hierarchies of religious authority and sexuality in Russia. With anarchist sentiment of anti-
authoritarianism and anti-capitalism, Pussy Riot uses musical protest to counter gender
stereotypes and break down structural inequality in anarcho-punk and mainstream society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My research shows anarchist sentiment has coincided with anarcho-punk subcultures
where women are foregrounded to voice their opinions and critiques of gendered society.
Women have continued to hold active and prominent roles in the anarcho-punk scene since the
‘70s despite the presence of dominating masculinity in societies and subcultures that attempt to
drown them out. Because of the nature of anarchist philosophy, sexism exists less prevalent in
anarcho-punk subcultures than in mainstream society, but it is difficult to completely detach an
entire subculture from a hegemonic society where gender norms frame the way we navigate
throughout life. It is important for future research to have an intersectional approach when
analyzing anarcha-feminism and punk culture to provide a better understanding of women in
punk in the modern-day and how it has progressed since the 20th-century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;secondary-sources&quot;&gt;Secondary Sources&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allen, G. (2011). &lt;em&gt;Artists' magazines: an alternative space for art.&lt;/em&gt; MIT Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D'Angelica, C. (2009). &lt;em&gt;Beyond Bikini Kill: A history of riot grrl, from grrls to ladies.&lt;/em&gt;
Sarah Lawrence College.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Davis, Matt. “Noam Chomsky: Writer, Linguist… Anarchist?” &lt;em&gt;Big Think,&lt;/em&gt; Big Think, 12
Sept. 2019, bigthink.com/politics-current-affairs/noam-chomsky-anarchist-beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Griffin, N. (2012). Gendered performance performing gender in the DIY Punk and
Hardcore Music Scene. &lt;em&gt;Journal of International Women's Studies, 13&lt;/em&gt;(2), 66-81.
Johnson, J. E. (2014). Pussy Riot as a feminist project: Russia's gendered informal
politics. Nationalities Papers, 42(4), 583-590.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leblanc, L. (1999). Pretty in Punk : Girls’ Gender Resistance in a Boys’ Subculture. New
Brunswick, N.J.: Rutgers University Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nicholas, L. (2007). Approaches to gender, power and authority in contemporary
anarcho-punk: poststructuralist anarchism?. &lt;em&gt;eSharp, 9,&lt;/em&gt; 1-21.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;primary-sources&quot;&gt;Primary Sources&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(2018). &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloudfront.crimethinc.com/assets/zines/fuck-abuse-kill-power/fuck-abuse-kill-
power_print_black_and_white.pdf&quot;&gt;Fuck Abuse, Kill Power.&lt;/a&gt; CrimesthInc.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pussy Riot. (2018). &lt;a href=&quot;https://genius.com/Pussy-riot-dave-sitek-bad-girls-lyrics&quot;&gt;“Bad Girls”.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/12/24/anarcho-punk-and-gender-politics/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/12/24/anarcho-punk-and-gender-politics/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New World Disorder: How Anarcho-Punks Said No to Iraq</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The early 2000’s punk movement expressed resentment towards the failures of the Bush
administration and the Iraq War. On March 20th, 2003, the Bush administration launched an
attack on Iraq without the approval of the U.N., legitimating its decision on the basis of hidden
weapons of mass destruction. During the 1980’s, Washington supplied Iraq’s dictator Saddam
Hussein with intelligence, aid, and whatever arms he desired (Murray, Scales Jr. 27). However,
this friendship quickly ended in a post-September 11 world, when the Bush administration’s
militaristic turn in foreign policy put human rights on the backburner and exacerbated the pain of
war for civilian Iraqis without being able to loosen Saddam’s iron grip (Murray, Scales Jr. 33;
Tarrow 10). U.S. leaders—politicians, military experts, and intelligence analysts did all in their
power to “sell” the war to the American public and suppressed the voices of protest (Tarrow 10).
The Iraq War had partially been driven by the United States’ capitalistic interests, since Iraq had
the greatest oil reserves of any nation after Saudi Arabia (Murray, Scales Jr. 19). Disillusioned
with the lies from their government, anarcho-punk youth grabbed their guitars and wrote anti-
war songs, mobilizing Americans to take political action. I argue that the punk subculture of the
early 2000’s contained anarchist principles in the countercultural, decentralized production
networks, collectivization methods, and direct action politics that mobilized youth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many anti-war songs evoke anger in order to make listeners question authority. Punk is
frequently caricatured by its evocative embrace of rage and violence, and as NPR radio host Rick
Karr noted, as long as there have been songs in America, there have been protest songs (2003).
Author Kevin Dunn gives an account of his own experience at a punk club in Portland, Oregon a
few blocks from his hotel when the U.S. was invading Iraq. Popular anti-war songs of the time contained variations of the phrase “blood for oil” in every chorus. Dunn recalls hearing lyrics
such as “Don’t give me no shit about blood, sweat, tears and toil / It’s all about the price of oil”
and “We need healthcare more than going to war / You think it’s democracy they’re fighting for?
/ Bush and Saddam should kick it like back in the day / With the cocaine and Courvoisier.” The
in-between song banter reflected comments about President George W. Bush, remarks about
American fascism, concerns about the impending War on Iraq, and pleas to register to vote
(Dunn 194). The bands were using the hard, angry music to make sense of the dangerous world
they found themselves in and helped young consumers become critical of the world they are
inheriting. Listening to punk was an inspiring experience through which one can quickly learn
about the secrets behind the Iraq War. Author Dylan Clark argues that punks, frustrated with the
social and political repression of contemporary life, turned to punk rock and directed their anger
at the “System,” or “sexist, homophobic, racist, and ecocidal corporate capitalism which
dominates people” (56). In its anti-capitalistic tendencies, the punk movement embodied
anarchism and became an important device for disrupting the pro-war status quo. One of the
elements that made punk significant was that it represented not just a form of musical expression,
but a social and political disruption giving artists freedom to express themselves. Punk provided
resources for disruption of the orderly sequence involved in the communication of dominant
social ideas and practices, such as the pro-war narratives in the media. It can disrupt the
authorized codes through which the social world is organized and experienced. The basic tenets
of punk have always been: no set of rules, no set of expectations, and that it always challenges
the status quo (Dunn 197). As we will see, the expectations for the music industry were set by a
centralized authority figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to anti-war messages being blacklisted on the radio, the punk subculture fought
against media conglomerates by creating alternative avenues to spread its message. Punk offered
a healthy resistance to dominant forces and social norms, whatever they may be, and this
message was conveyed not just in the lyrics of punk music, but in the entirety of punk. During
the anti-Vietnam War movement in the 1970s, as NPR host Rick Karr explains, record
companies and radio broadcasters could embrace songs with anti-war messages, but that freedom
has evaporated as media conglomerates have taken over the record and radio industries and
shunned anything that might alienate even one listener (2003). Capitalist media firms did not
invest in young musicians who wrote protest songs because they had to sell records and time on
the radio stations (Karr 2003). In response to this media censorship, the punk movement’s do-it-
yourself (DIY) ethos demanded that listeners move beyond the role of consumers and instead
become actively involved by distributing self-produced zines, organizing shows (often in
atypical venues, such as basements of houses), or starting their own bands (a frequently cited
excerpt from an early punk zine, for example, contains a diagram of three guitar chords and
features the caption, “Now Form a Band”) (Barrett 26). Punks strove to eliminate the distinctions
between performers and audience, and did so by the anarchist principle of egalitarianism: anyone
could be a punk, and any punk could play in a band, publish a zine, organize shows, or produce
or distribute records. An anti-establishment, decentralized disposition is the defining anarchist
element of the genre. The movement itself has offered no established leadership to be co-opted,
either by big business or political parties. In response to big companies silencing anti-war
messages, punk culture deconstructed and subverted the social order of radio air-time and
parodied the position of a CEO. By finding a more productive and less destructive way of
fighting against the status quo, punk rock works within and against the hegemony of capitalist telecommunication networks. Rather than protesting to gain access to dominant institutions,
organizers built their own alternatives. In other words, punk culture is anti-hierarchical and
cooperative, functioning as a relatively autonomous space in society and providing musicians
with resources for agency and empowerment. Against the rise of neoliberalism which aimed to
destroy the very idea of communal spaces, punk rock sought to carve out a space that was closed
to the market and controlled by the community that used it.
Along with the basic tenet of decentralization, the early 2000’s punk subculture contained
the anarchist principle of collectivization. Anarchism has historically been a pronounced feature
of the punk field as evidenced by various anarcho-punk collectives (Dunn 200). Punk can be
linked to the anarchist New Left inspired organization of cooperative counter-institutions that
began in the late 1960s (Barrett 25). From the 1960s onward, collectives such as cooperative
bookstores, coffee shops, and grocery stores began to spring up and were organized according to
three basic principles: consensus-based decision-making, voluntary participation, and relatively
horizontal leadership structures (Barrett 25). The punk movement as a whole has thrived under a
network of local “scenes” with no central authority. In their collectives they not only organize
concerts and promote punk music but have their own workshops for study, analysis, and political
education (Dunn 208). The collectivist impulses led members of the punk subculture to do
significant organizational work, not only confronting dominant power structures but also proving
less isolated from the rest of society than they are often presented. Instead of petitioning the
powerful for inclusion, the punk movement has built its own elaborate network of counter-
structures, including music venues, media, record labels, and distributors that have operated as
cultural and economic alternatives to the entertainment industry and sites of resistance to the Iraq
War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notable punk bands that were against the Iraq War used their bombastic lyrics to
mobilize youth for the anarchist principle of direct action. Green Day’s album American Idiot is
a pointed political critique of the George W. Bush administration and contemporary American
life, and the band combined their performances with calls for political action and involvement
among the audiences. As an example, the band would regularly pull members of the audience on
stage, hand them instruments, teach them a few chords, and have them join the band in a cover of
Operation Ivy’s anti-war song ‘Unity’ (Dunn 202). The fact that Green Day signed to a major
media corporation and still retained their anti-status quo disposition exposed a greater expanse of
youth to an alternative point of view that they are not necessarily going to hear on the news or
from their parents. Green Day’s high profile benefit for Food Not Bombs raised $500,000 to feed
homeless (Dunn 204). High-profile punk bands have the resources to resist neoliberal hegemony
while also providing a means to directly give back to the community. NOFX released a scathing
critique of the Bush administration with their American Errorist CD. The lead singer created
punkvoter.com with the ultimate goal to educate, register and mobilize over 500,000 youths to be
an electoral force (Dunn 208). This exemplifies the fact that punk offers the possibility for
activism when the personal is political. While there are no punk politics per se, punk can produce
a disposition that is inherently political in nature. The DIY ethos and anarchist sympathies within
punk provide valuable resources for political engagement that is both local and disturbing to pro-
war advocates. Punk rock has always been on the edge and in the forefront of politics. Punk, as a
youth culture that nurtures a healthy skepticism of authority, serves as a stepping stone towards
more formal political activism. Punk’s direct, participatory nature of DIY politics constituted a
direct action approach to politics—a congruence of “means and ends.” Punk is about getting
involved, not tuning in and dropping out. Youth respond to their environment with proactive organization. DIY punk ventures necessitate the development of basic organizing skills, such as
designing and distributing flyers, monitoring crowds, and negotiating with police and neighbors
(Barrett 38). Punk’s DIY ethos and the resource it offers for resisting the multiple forms of
alienation in modern society is a key tenet of anarchist direct action politics. For the youth
involved, the word punk is a synonym of struggle and commitment. It energized disenfranchised
youths in the Bush-era and mobilized them to make a change a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The punk subculture must then be credited, at least to some extent, to the large number of
protesters during the global anti-Iraq war movement. On February 15, 2003, millions of people
around the world combined in the largest example of collective action in history to protest
against the impending war on Iraq (Tarrow 7). The Institute for Policy Studies, a collection of
scholar-activists, wrote a piece on how across the globe, the call came in scores of languages,
‘the world says no to war!’ and the cry ‘Not in Our Name’ echoed from millions of voices
(Bennis 2013). The Guinness Book of World Records said between 12 and 14 million people
came out that day, the largest protest in the history of the world (Bennis 2013). It was, as British
labor and peace activist Tony Benn described it to the million Londoners in the streets that day,
‘the first global demonstration, and its first cause is to prevent a war against Iraq’ (Bennis 2013).
Interestingly, this event was a global protest against a war that had not yet begun — the goal, to
try to stop it. While we did not prevent the Iraq war, the protests proved its clear illegality,
demonstrated the isolation of the Bush administration policies, helped prevent war in Iran, and
inspired a generation of activists (Bennis 2013). As one speaker at the event noted, ‘We stand
here today because our right to dissent, and our right to participate in a real democracy has been
hijacked by those who call for war’ (Bennis 2013). It was something new in the history of
contentious politics yet also drawn from anarchist principles: a concerted campaign of transnational collective action—using means of mobilization—which brought millions of people
together around common goals and against common targets. In a way, the anarchist anti-war
sympathies within punk DIY culture spread from local scenes into global networks that reached
millions, one of punk music’s biggest successes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, early 2000’s DIY punk music began from anger and disillusionment about
the Iraq War, then made into full records, then performed for friends, that then led to a wider
direct action movement. Punk music during this era was anarchist in that it took a decentralized
route of distributing its anti-war message, straying away from big media corporations. The angry,
in-your-face lyrics helped fuel collectivist organization as a way of expressing resentment
towards the Bush administration's war on terror, the Iraq War, and the negative effects of
globalization and neoliberalism. Through connecting anger in music to anger in street protests,
punk music changed many people’s consciousness about what was happening and shaped
American culture. Punk has always been about asking “why” and then doing something about it.
It is about looking at the world around and asking “Why are things as fucked up as they are?”
And then it’s about looking inwards at yourself and asking “Why aren’t I doing anything about
this?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;works-cited&quot;&gt;Works Cited&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barrett, Dawson. &lt;a href=&quot;www.jstor.org/stable/41809730&quot;&gt;“DIY Democracy: The Direct Action Politics of U.S. Punk Collectives.”&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;American Studies,&lt;/em&gt; vol. 52, no. 2, 2013, pp. 23–42. JSTOR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bennis, Phyllis. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ipsdc.org/february_15_2003_the_day_the_world_said_no_to_war/&quot;&gt;“February 15, 2003. The Day the World Said No to War.”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Institute for Policy
Studies,&lt;/em&gt; 2 May 2014,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clark, Dylan. &lt;a href=&quot;www.jstor.org/stable/42590265&quot;&gt;“Notes: Music and the Education of Anger.”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Thought,&lt;/em&gt; vol. 36, no. 2,
2001, pp. 55–60. JSTOR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dunn, Kevin C. &lt;a href=&quot;www.jstor.org/stable/20542757&quot;&gt;“Never Mind the Bollocks: The Punk Rock Politics of Global Communication.”&lt;/a&gt;
Review of International Studies, vol. 34, 2008, pp. 193–210. JSTOR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Murray, Williamson, and Scales Jr. Robert H. &lt;em&gt;The Iraq War: a Military History.&lt;/em&gt; The Belknap
Press of Harvard University Press, 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://proxy.lib.umich.edu/login?url=https://search-proquest-
com.proxy.lib.umich.edu/docview/2253376464?accountid=14667&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Musical Protests of Vietnam War &amp;amp; War in Iraq.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; NPR, Washington, D.C., 2003. &lt;em&gt;ProQuest,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tarrow, Sidney. &lt;a href=&quot;www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/j.cttts43x&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The World Says No to War: Demonstrations against the War on Iraq.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Edited by
Stefaan Walgrave and Dieter Rucht, NED - New edition ed., vol. 33, University of
Minnesota Press, 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/12/24/new-world-disorder/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/12/24/new-world-disorder/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Esperanto: A History</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MG8Wzm0GXQg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/12/19/esperanto-a-history/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/12/19/esperanto-a-history/</guid>
        
        <category>Video</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
